Guide to the Adella Fowler Larkin Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Adella Fowler Larkin correspondence
1859-1895
GEN MSS 921
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.46
(4 boxes)
The collection consists of letters sent to New England resident Adella Fowler Larkin by her family and friends during the second half of the nineteenth century. The letters are personal in nature and discuss people, fashion, news, events, health, and activities of the correspondents. Prominent in the collection are letters from her sister Myra Fowler McFarland, a teacher with the American Missionary Association working in Florida, South Carolina, and Georgia before, during, and immediately after the Civil War, and letters from her stepbrother George B. Pratt, a newspaperman writing from Ohio and Wisconsin. Also present are nine installments of the "Milwaukee bad boy" stories by George W. Peck clipped from an unidentified newspaper, a valentine published by T. W. Strong, New York, and an advertising circular from Lucy Guild of Rupert, Vermont, promoting her Crystal Palace Chart for dressmaking.
Larkin, Adella Fowler, 1850-1917
Peck, George W. (George Wilbur), 1840-1916
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Edward J. Cohen on the Edith and Richard French Fund, 2004. Gift of Edward J. Cohen, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Fowler Family Tree
Family members whose letters are prominent in the collection are underlined.
See also The Twining Family, by Thomas Jefferson Twining (Fort Wayne, Indiana: 1905)
TITUS FOWLER (1738-1827) m. Hannah Burritt (d. 1865)
- -1 CHAUNCEY BURRITT FOWLER (1771-1855) m. 1788 Apphia Twining (1774-1843)
- -- -2 Almira Fowler (1798-1865) m. 1823 John Hastings Allen (1794-1854)
- -- -2 Hannah Fowler (1800-1850) m. 1835 Percival Davison (1801-1876)
- -- -- -3 Maria Louise Davison (b. 1836) m. 1862 Norton W. Millard (1825-1904)
- -- -- -3 Edmund Davison (1839-1905) m. 1870 Olive J. Chapman (b. 1837)
- -- -2 Alanson Fowler (1802-1894) m. Sarah Eliza Miller (1811-1901)
- -- -- -3 Milton Alanson Fowler (1835-1911) m. 1859 Catherine (Kate) Putnam Sikes (1838-1905)
- -- -- -- -4 Clarence Alanson Fowler (1864-1926)
- -- -- -- -4 Henry Thatcher Fowler (1867-1948) m. 1897 Harriet N. Nesmith
- -- -2 Chauncey B. Fowler (1804-1850)
- -- -2 PEREZ MARSHALL FOWLER (1806-1904) m 1. 1839 Lois Elvira Miller (1818-1855)
- -- -- -3 Chauncey B. Fowler (1842-1850)
- -- -- -3 ADELLA HANNAH FOWLER (1850-1917) m. 1871 James E. Larkin (1844-1936)
- -- -- -- -4 Anna May Larkin (b. 1877)
- -- -- -- -4 Harold Fowler Larkin (1884-1966)
- -- -- -- -4 Edna Winfield Larkin (b. 1885)
- -- -- -3 Ella L. Fowler (1854-1926) raised by Alanson Fowler; m. 1874 Oscar Shann (d. 1935)
- -- -- -- -4 Mabel Shann
- -- -- -- -4 John Shann
- -- -- -- -4 Oscar Shann
- -- -- -- -4 Catherine Shann
- -- -- -- -4 Elsie Shann
- -- -- -m 2. (by 1865) Ann R. Pratt (1815-1881); widow of Austin G. Pratt (1815-1854)
- -- -- -3 George B. Pratt (1846-1890 m. 1872 Lolla Davis (1851-1890)
- -- -- -- -4 Stephen Austin Pratt (1875-1956)
- -- -- -- -4 Clarence Davis Pratt (1881-1964)
- -- -2 Apphia Fowler (1808-1898) m. 1838 Alonzo J. Maltbie (1814-1900)
- -- -- -3 Anna F. Maltbie (1847-1866)
- -- -- -3 Louise H. Maltbie (b. 1849) m. 1867 William C. Pasco (1847-1900)
- -- -- -- -4 Harry A. Pasco (b. 1868)
- -- -- -- -4 Alva C. Pasco (1869-1869)
- -- -- -- -4 Minnie L. Pasco (b. 1871)
- -- -- -- -4 Herbert W. Pasco (b. 1876)
- -- -- -- -4 Jule C. Pasco (b. 1890)
- -- -2 Ann Twining Fowler (1810-1842) m. 1836 Pliny S. Mills
- -- -- -3 Josephine Mills (b. 1838) adopted by Alanson Fowler; m. 1861 Henry Tyler Phillips (d. 1901)
- -- -- -- -4 Anna Cecilia Phillips (b. 1864)
- -- -- -- -4 Harry F. Phillips (b. 1865)
- -- -- -- -4 Eugenia Tyler Phillips (b. 1869)
- -- -- -- -4 Estella Josephine Phillips (b. 1876)
- -- -- -3 Almira (Myra) Mills (1840-1925) adopted by Perez Fowler; m. 1878 William D. McFarland (1851-1932)
- -- -- -3 Theodore Mills (1842-1915) adopted by Apphia Fowler Maltbie; m. 1867 Louise A. Jewett (b. 1842)
- -- -- -- -4 Annie Louise Maltbie (b. 1875)
- -- -- -- -4 William Mills Maltbie (b. 1880)
Adella Fowler Larkin (1850-1917)
Adella Hannah Fowler, known to her family as Della, was born in Tolland Center, Massachusetts, on July 6, 1850, the daughter of Perez Marshall Fowler (1806-1904) and his first wife Lois Elvira Miller Fowler (1818-1855). She attended the Hudson River Institute in Claverack, New York, nearby the home of her maternal aunt and uncle Sarah and Alanson Fowler, in the mid-1860s, and settled in Winsted, Connecticut, after marrying merchant James Edwin Larkin (1844-1936) on November 22, 1871. Adella Fowler Larkin was a member of the Daughters of the American Revolution through her great-grandfather Titus Fowler; she died in Winsted on June 22, 1917.
Myra Fowler McFarland (1840-1925)
Almira Mills Fowler was born on February 16, 1840, one of three children of Ann Twining Fowler (1810-1842) and her husband Pliny S. Mills of New York. Upon the death of their mother, the Mills children were adopted by their maternal uncles and aunt; Almira was raised by Perez Fowler and his first and second wives Lois and Ann. She was also known as Almyra, Mira, and Myra, the latter the forename she used most of her adult life. She was teaching in Newport, Wakulla County, Florida, in 1860-1861, and then was among the first teachers sent by the American Missionary Association to the Port Royal Experiment, a pre-Reconstruction effort to support freed slaves in working and managing the cotton plantations on the South Carolina Sea Islands which had been abandoned by owners fleeing the Union troops. Myra Fowler was assigned to Ashdale plantation on Ladys Island near Beaufort, where she taught school from December 1862 to April 1864, afterward teaching at The Oaks plantation, and then in Augusta, Georgia, from November 1866 through May 1867. In 1878 she married the Reverend William D. McFarland, pastor of Congregationalist churches in Simsbury, East Granby, and Shelburne Falls, Connecticut, moving with him to Baltimore in 1884. Through the American Missionary Association Myra McFarland also taught at Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee, from the mid-1880s to the early 1890s, and at the Illinois State Training School in Geneva, where she was working in 1910. By 1912 she had returned to live in Tennessee, and had been spending the summer of 1925 with a niece in Granby, Connecticut, when she died there on August 1, 1925.
George B. Pratt (1846-1890)
George B. Pratt was born in New Boston, Massachusetts, on February 24, 1848, the son of Austin G. Pratt (1815-1854) and his wife Ann R. Pratt (1815-1881), who became the second wife of Perez M. Fowler. Pratt graduated from the Westfield Normal School, Westfield, Massachusetts, and in 1866 went west to Fremont, Ohio, where he became connected with the Fremont Journal. He continued in the business, eventually editing and owning papers in Milan, Oberlin, and Norwalk, Ohio. In 1877 Pratt purchased the Menasha Press, in Menasha, Wisconsin; in 1881 he sold the paper to became a general publisher, and founded the Art Publishing Company in 1883.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters sent to New England resident Adella Fowler Larkin by her family and friends during the second half of the nineteenth century. The letters are personal in nature and discuss people, fashion, news, events, health, and activities of the correspondents. Prominent in the collection are letters from her sister Myra Fowler McFarland, a teacher working with African American freedmen under the auspices of the American Missionary Association in Florida, South Carolina, and Georgia before, during, and immediately after the Civil War. Also prominent are letters from her stepbrother George B. Pratt, a newspaperman writing from Ohio and Wisconsin.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Letters from Family, 1859-1895. II. Letters from Friends, 1862-1892.
African Americans -- Education -- 19th century; Freedmen -- United States; Port Royal (S.C.) Expedition, 1861; Teachers -- Florida; Teachers -- Georgia; Teachers -- South Carolina; Claverack (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Ladies Island (S.C.) -- Social life and customs; Sandisfield (Mass.: Town) -- Social life and customs; Tolland (Mass.: Town) -- Social life and customs; Menasha (Wis.) -- Social life and customs; Sea Islands -- Social life and customs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Valentines -- United States -- 19th century; Teachers -- United States -- 19th century; Fowler, Ann R. Pratt, 1815-1881; Fowler family; Guild, Lucy; Irwin, Emergene Twining, 1843-1931; Larkin, Adella Fowler, 1850-1917; McFarland, Myra Fowler, 1840-1925; Moeller, Elisabeth Thatcher; Peck, George W. (George Wilbur), 1840-1916; Pratt, George B., 1846-1890; Shann, Ella Fowler, 1854-1926; Strong, Thomas W., 1817-1892; American Missionary Association; Hudson River Institute and Claverack Academy
- Letters from Family, 1859-1895; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds letters sent to Adella Fowler Larkin by members of her family, including her sisters Almira and Ella, stepbrother George Pratt, aunt Sarah, and various cousins. Prominent among them are nine folders of letters sent by Myra Fowler McFarland from her teaching positions in Florida, South Carolina, and Georgia before, during, and immediately after the Civil War. Her last folder holds nine episodes of the "Milwaukee Bad Boy" stories by George W. Peck clipped from an unidentified newspaper. Also notable are Pratt's letters which encouraged James and Adella Larkin to join him in Wisconsin, as well as those of his visiting mother, Ann R. Fowler, which describe family matters and her views of life in Wisconsin.
  - Fowler, Ann R. Pratt, 1864-1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Fowler, Milton and Catherine (Kate), 1880-1887 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fowler, Sarah Miller, 1861-1882 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Ham, Augusta and Emma, 1860-1866 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Irwin, Emergene (Genie) Twining, 1862-1868 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Larkin family members, 1864-1877 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - McFarland, Myra Fowler, 1860-1895, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-18)
  - Maltbie, Anna Fowler, 1860-1865 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Maltbie, Theodore Mills, 1866, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Pratt, George B., Lolla, and Clarence, 1862-1890, undated (Box 3, Folder 21-24)
    General note
    Includes one letter from Adella Fowler to George Pratt, January 4, 1865
  - Shann, Ella L. Fowler, 1859-1882 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Letters to other family members, 1868-1881 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Includes letters to Perez and Ann R. Fowler from siblings and children, and to James E. Larkin
- Letters from Friends, 1862-1892; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  The letters in this series are primarily from childhood friends from Massachusetts writing to Adella Fowler at school in Claverack, New York, covering topics including local activities, friends, and family.
  - Moeller, Elisabeth (Lizzie) Thatcher, 1863-1868, undated (Box 4, Folder 28-30)
  - Pike, Susan M. Traver, 1862-1869 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Friends from Sandisfield, Massachusetts, 1864-1868 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Friends from Tolland, Massachusetts, 1862-1866 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Friends from Westfield, Massachusetts, 1862-1864 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Other friends, 1863-1873 (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
  - Printed ephemera, circa 1865, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Includes a valentine published by T. W. Strong, New York, and an advertising circular from Lucy Guild of Rupert, Vermont, promoting her Crystal Palace Chart for dressmaking